Spatsizi is
three times the size of Yellowstone Park,
and that whole Stikine protected
area is actually over a million hectares.
It's huge.
My name's Carrie Collingwood.
I live in Smithers, British Columbia.
I was born and raised here.
I have lived here pretty much all my life.
Decided to move back to Smithers to
actually work for my dad and my uncle in.
So that's easy.
the North was calling me, so I.
I came back and started fly fish
guiding in Spatsizi Wilderness Park,
and started managing their guide
outfitting business and spent 20 years
there after university.
But I also spent my youth in Spatsizi.
We guided people from all over the world.
A lot of people from the United States,
a lot of people from Europe, Norway.
And they were just mesmerised
by the beauty of the area.
And I think it was just a combination of
there was no it there's no industrial
development in the park.
There's no roads.
Access is either you're hiking in
or you're flying in or you're horseback
riding in.
And it
I used to trail horses out of Spatsizi.
or in. It would take us three days
to get to the headwaters of this Stikine.
So we would put on hundreds of kilometres,
from the nearest road to get into Spatsizi.
That is a truly unique, special area.
It's got
huge population of moose, caribou, stone,
sheep, mountain goats, grizzly bears.
It's its own ecosystem in itself.
There's also challenges with that area
because you have encroachment
outside of the park.
So you have mines and industrial activity
that are being developed
and have been proposed for many years.
And wildlife don't know park boundaries.
So for example, caribou,
they're their, nursing
grounds are outside of the protected area
on the west side of
Spatsizi.
And that area is not protected.
So it would be nice to see more buffer
zones, areas of high density of wildlife,
particularly caribou,
which their populations are declining.
Whether it's climate change
in industrial activity
encroaching on the park.
They need special attention
and and more protection.
My dad has witnessed in the last 50 years.
He saw the decline of caribou.
While he was quite outfitting and unfortunately
there was not much
that was done to help protect them.
And we we need to do more research
and definitely
look at other areas
that are in the Stikine country
and beyond to continue
to protect wildlife.
For me,
it's just a special place that I believe
also should be accessible, like people
should, not accessible in the fact
that we should build roads into this area.
But people should be able to go in
and be able to hike, hunt, fish because
because once
you have a connection to place
and you have a connection to
land, you have conservation.
So, that's why Spatsizi
is special to me,
because I have a connection
to to that place
because I've spent time there.
And that's why anglers, hunters,
if we have access
to these places to be able to recreate,
then we are going to have conservation,
people are going to care about them.
And studies show that anglers, hunters,
those areas are actually more
protected than areas that are not
because of that conservation piece,
because of that connection.